<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A New discovery of the sham-Presbyterian plot, or, The substance of the information of James Carol given in upon oath before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of London, July 1681 : together with an account of the apprehension of one Lamport an Irish papist, that endeavoured to suborn the said Carol, the said Lamport being seized in his bed the 10th of this instant August.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12637147</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12637147</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 448:18, 966:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A New discovery of the sham-Presbyterian plot, or, The substance of the information of James Carol given in upon oath before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of London, July 1681 : together with an account of the apprehension of one Lamport an Irish papist, that endeavoured to suborn the said Carol, the said Lamport being seized in his bed the 10th of this instant August.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Entry for N629 cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carol, James.</term>
               <term>Lamport, Peter.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A NEW DISCOVERY OF THE Sham-Presbyterian Plot. OR,
<list>
                  <item>The ſubſtance of the Information of <hi>James Carol,</hi> given in upon Oath before the Right Honourable the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> of <hi>LONDON,</hi> July 1681.</item>
                  <item>Together with an Account of the Apprehenſion of one <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, that endeavoured to ſuborn the ſaid <hi>Carol.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Lamport</hi> being ſeized in his Bed the 10th. of this Inſtant <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Information of <hi>James Carol</hi> a Proteſtant <hi>Engliſhman</hi> late of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and firſt Diſcoverer of the horrid Popiſh Plot in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the Year 1672. ſworn, and examined before the Right Honourable Sr. <hi>Patient Ward</hi> Knight <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That he hath been enforced to expend, and been at above 1000. l. Damages by the unjuſt Proſecutions of Papiſts of great Power in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by reaſon of his Diſcovery of an Horrid Popiſh Plot carrying on in that Kingdom in 1672. which has been to the utter Ruine of Himſelf and his Family; His Wife dying big with Child in 1680. of Blows received from the Papiſts; and this Informant narrowly eſcaping with his Life: That in 1673. he was dealt with to retract his Evidence, and tempted thereunto with the promiſed reward of 500 l. But the Informant Refuſed to be prevailed with, conſidering the everlaſting Damage he muſt incur by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Actions: That about the beginning of <hi>June</hi> laſt, the Informant happened to meet with one <hi>Peter Lamport,</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, and pretended Merchant, whoſe Lodging was in <hi>Roſemary-Lane,</hi> who inviting this Informant to drink a Diſh of Coffee with him at Mr. <hi>Bridges</hi> Coffee-houſe in Popes-head Ally, over againſt the Royal Exchange, carryed him into an obſcure and remote part of the Room a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and then and there told this Deponent, That there had a long time been a great talk of a Popiſh Plot; But ſhortly it would be proved by many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, That it was only a Presbyterian Plot; and That thoſe that had endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make out a Popiſh Plot, would be ſeized and hang'd, if they would not turn it on the Presbyterians; And that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and ſeveral other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Lords and others, would be ſeiz'd and ſent to the Tower; abuſing them, and many others, with many opprobrious and ſcandalous Names: And added,
<pb facs="tcp:64920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>That <hi>Fitz Harris</hi> is a great Rogue, and would be hang'd, although he now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the Presbyterians imployed him, and will do any thing in hopes that his Majeſty will pardon him; But there is the word of a King for it, He ſhall dye, for ther's no truſting him. You ſee, (ſaid the ſaid <hi>Lamport,</hi> further directing his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to this Informant) how you and others have been ſlighted a long time; Therefore take my Advice, be you concern'd in making it out to be a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Plot. The Informant demanded, in what Particulars he might do it, and pray'd him to explain his mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lamport</hi> replyed—I am ſure you underſtand me well enough; it is to be a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Plot, and you will be eaſily believed and credited, having of late been converſant with them, and now is the time to make your own Terms; and were I in your caſe, I would make good Terms for my ſelf. It will be the making of you: Therefore do not loſe the Opportunity. To all which, the Informant made him only general civil Anſwers, and ſo for that time they parted.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That a Week or thereabouts afterwards, the ſaid <hi>Lamport</hi> met him in Tower-ſtreet, and then demanded of him, what he thought of the Diſcourſe they had the other day. This Informant replyed, I believe Sir, you are concern'd, and know much of theſe Affairs, as to the making it out to be a Presbyterian Plot. Then the ſaid <hi>Lamport</hi> ſwore, That he did know as much as any man, and more than this Informant would believe; And that this Informant might take what he ſaid for Truth: For (ſaid he) did I not tell you, That ſome of the Lords would be ſeiz'd on ſuddenly, and ſent to the Tower? and don't you find my words to be true?</p>
            <p>The Informant anſwered, That he found ſome of his words to be true, for he had heard that the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> was Committed, and that he remembred their laſt Diſcourſe very well. Yes, ſays <hi>Lamport,</hi> and you will hear of many more Warrants for the ſecuring of ſeveral perſons, for having an hand in this <hi>Presbyterian</hi>-Plot, and they ſent to the <hi>Tower</hi> e're it be long. Therefore are you yet concern'd or imploy'd in the Buſineſs? To which this Informant, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſift his Intentions, replied,—I have, Sir, been towards <hi>Whitehal,</hi> ſince you gave me that advice. That's well, ſaid <hi>Lamport,</hi> take my counſel, and you'l do well; be concern'd, and neglect not your time, for you'll never have ſuch another opportunity. And ſo again we parted.</p>
            <p>Suddenly after the ſaid <hi>Lamport,</hi> as I was credibly informed, went for <hi>France;</hi> and on the 26th of <hi>July</hi> I diſcovered this whole Tranſaction upon Oath, to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor. And underſtanding ſince, That the ſaid <hi>Lamport</hi> was returned into <hi>England,</hi> on the 10th of this inſtant <hi>Auguſt</hi> he was ſeized in his Bed in <hi>Roſemary</hi>-Lane aforeſaid; and being carried before Juſtice <hi>Rycroft,</hi> I there again teſtified the Truth of the Premiſes againſt him.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-head Ally,</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
